he's competed in CrossFit he's run
marathons and now he's the World's
Strongest Man tipping the scales at over
350 lbs but he's also doing bar
muscleups at over 350 lbs this guy's
athletic as they come had some really
interesting things to say about body fat
if you go into prejudging that's where
the competition's happening men's open
is different you know you have to be on
for men's open you have to be on both
nights they can change their body just
on like how much salt they have over the
course of a couple hours you never want
to hear about an athlete ending a run at
something like the Olympic Games because
of an injury Maddie Rogers is 28 years
old and I got to be honest my heart goes
out to
her hey folks welcome to strength weekly
the weekly update show that keeps you in
the know yeah in the know on everything
from around the barbell game I'm David
Thomas to I'm joined by Phil bman we're
bringing this to you on behalf of
barbend make sure you subscribe to
barbend and we'll keep you up to date
with everything that you need to know
about strong people this week we're
covering a Litany of topics hotty shupin
win again is he Unstoppable heading into
the Olympia we recap his Arnold Classic
UK title Maddie Rogers the noted and
very popular American weightlifter is
out of contention for the Paris Olympics
because of an injury we go into that
including her messaging on social media
wishing Maddie a speedy recovery
Victoria long also partially due to
injury retiring from the sport of strong
woman giving her one of the most epic
yet shortest runs in the history of the
professional ranks of that Sport and
Mitchell Hooper reigning World's
Strongest Man and Arnold strongman
classic Champion breaking down ideal
body composition for strength athletes
here's why Mitchell might be one of the
best athletes in the world to pay
attention to on this because guess what
he's not just an athlete he's also a
clinician Phil which of these stories
are you most excited about today I think
talking about Victoria Long's uh history
as short as it may be in strong woman is
Immaculate and to see her retiring so
soon after being so dominant for such a
short period of time I mean what a
historic marker for the sport I think is
Victoria Long's career and I'm just
gonna foreshadow folks I'm gonna call
Victoria long later in this broadcast
I'm gonna call her the Sandy kofax of
strong woman and we're going to get into
exactly why but first up hottie he is on
a tear after edging out Samson Duda for
the Arnold Classic bodybuilding title in
the men's open division in Columbus he
repeats in the UK also edging out Samson
who finished in second place some
interesting things happened further down
the ranks and actually to round out the
podium but hottie um the bodybuilder
from Iran Arnold quip that he might have
looked better than he did in Columbus
just a couple weeks prior uh what did we
think of the shape and the package that
uh HTI brought to the stage in the UK
Phil it was pretty much just a absolute
runback of the two two weeks prior in
Columbus where hotti shupin conditioning
keeps him on top of the division without
Dereck lford in the mix at these
contests so he goes over Duda in the
same fashion that he did in Columbus it
was really it came down to the
conditioning once again that puts him
over the top hotti in his own level
regardless of who he's next to in the
conditioning aspect of the sport so
that's where everybody else is going to
need to catch up if they're going to
beat shupin going into the 2024 Olympia
I'm sure Lansford is keenly aware of
where he needs to make up ground in
terms of his conditioning against shupin
as well daa still has the size if can
get the conditioning to compete at hotti
level then we might see him actually be
able to scale the ranks even further
last year he got bronze at the Olympia
I'm sure we're going to see him again at
the Olympia in 2024 he's already
qualified he doesn't need a win because
he was on the podium and then the big uh
result coming out of the UK was a Keem
Williams he goes from six up to third
he's doing really strong Tyler Manion of
the ifbb he mentioned on his social as
he recapped the Arnold Classic in
Columbus he said that athletes need to
be on their game in prejudging that's
where the majority of the judging
happens it happens in prejudging and
then finals is just to solidify what
they determined in prejudging unless
there's any major cases but for the most
part if you go into prejudging that's
where the competition's happening so
athletes need to be keenly aware that
that is where they need to be at their
best now we saw at the Arnold and
Columbus that AEM he was in seventh uh
uh in prejudging and he was able to move
up a rank in the finals but had he been
what he was in the finals during
prejudging he may have been much closer
to what his Arnold Classic UK rank was
and that's where you know you have to be
on for men's open you have to be on both
nights they get prejudging on one night
and finals on another night that is
different from all the other divisions
that usually do prejudging in the
morning and finals of the that night the
same day men's open is different and so
it's a different combo as like they can
change their body just on like how much
salt they have over the course of a
couple hours so it's it's a much tighter
tight RPP to walk in men's open and I
think we saw that AE had probably what I
would argue is the biggest result in the
UK based off of what he did in Columbus
yeah and he uh Leap Frogs Jonathan
delosa and James holling head um who
beat him who outplaced him at the Arnold
in Columbus and leap frogs them in the
UK and finishes on the podium so big
result for AEM definitely came in dialed
in uh I do want to say Samson Duda
someone who struggled with health issues
between the two competitions in those
two weeks uh he posted on social that he
felt his body was breaking down seems
like he might have gotten um an
infection or an illness and saw a doctor
and was on antibiotics so uh impressive
to see Samson bounce back um from a
position where we weren't sure we'd see
him compete and like health issues were
potentially significant according to him
so good to see him healthier uh we
talked a little bit last week about the
frequency of competition for some of
these athletes staying peaked four weeks
at a time at these low body fat
percentages Samson said on social media
that you know it he thinks it took a
toll on his immune system and it takes a
toll on his immune system if you want
that you can check out strength weekly
last week where we talked about hey
should there be a limit on how
frequently Pros can compete um obviously
curious as to everyone else's thoughts
so let us know in the comments this
basically sets up hottie by the way just
to recap as the person to potentially
take back the Mr Olympia title from
Derrick Lunsford Lunsford we will not
see compete until the Olympia makes it
very exciting I can't wait to see that
head-to-head potentially some pose Downs
just an exciting bodybuilding season on
the men's open side for sure Phil yeah I
think that now that we've seen where
hotti has come in like clearly he made
improvements since the Olympia like he's
clearly the number one Contender I think
where our eyes need to shift to now is
other top contenders that aren't that
didn't compete at the Arnold at either
Arnold this year are guys like Nick
Walker who's recovering from an injury
he was on the podium at the Olympia
before he got injured and he's going to
be back competing at the New York Pro
that's going to be his return since the
injury so we're going to see it what
kind of changes he has made to his
physique since then because the question
is okay it's hottie versus Derek at the
olymp with Samson in the mix maybe AEM
in the mix but there are still guys like
Hunter Labrada Nick Walker where's
Andrew Jack like we haven't seen those
guys since the Olympia and so now we're
goingon to have to look at where are the
other guys at the top of the card that
we're going to see trying to compete and
Edge out those guys at the top and what
adjustments can they make before we get
to the Olympia in the fall well moving
on we're going to move on to the sport
of weightlifting not a physique sport
more of a sport where you just have to
lift a certain amount of weight and lift
the most Maddie Rogers longtime popular
member of Team USA 28 years old has
withdrawn herself from contention for
the Paris Olympics now she competed in
Tokyo in 2021 didn't have the result I
think that she wanted in Tokyo and it
was actually very clear on on social
media that you know her performance on
the day was was not up to what she was
hoping she was a potential metal
Contender I mean she's a multi-time
World's medalist right Brian Oliver
who's an independent correspondent uh
for with with barbend point that point
that out very important Brian's opinions
do not necessarily reflect those of
barbend he actually was among the first
to report this for barbend and uh I
think did a uh in my personal opinion a
stellar job because you never want to
hear about an
athlete ending a run at something like
the Olympic Games because of an injury
Matty Rogers is 28 years old she has a
lot of experience under her belt when it
comes to lifting and performing at a
high level that being said it was an
extraordinary uphill battle for her to
potentially qualify for the Olympic team
this year because the US can only send
three women they can only send three
women in weightlifting to the Paris
Olympics and right now the leaders for
those are Olivia
Reeves Jordan De La Cruz and Mary Tyson
Lin right those are kind of the three
Front Runners Sarah robl has withdrawn
herself from contention so I will say I
think the chances that Matty would have
qualified for the Olympics and been
selected to the team were actually
pretty low given the fact that de crew
Reeves and Tyson Lin are like so far out
ahead in the rankings but Rogers was
eligible she was top 10 in her weight
category ranked worldwide so she was
eligible for selection I think it was
unlikely she would have been selected
she did withdraw from a competition
fairly recently you know right before
the European weightlifting championships
and uh I gotta be honest my heart goes
out to her uh you know I've spent some
time with Maddie I think she's a really
cool person um I like that she's very
public with the ups and downs of being a
professional weightlifter it does seem
like an injury that she can bounce back
from uh Phil do you want to talk a
little bit about you know what she said
is going on yeah she said about her
injuries she said quote lifting has been
an absolute nightmare it's like there's
a power outage in one whole in in one
whole leg plus being stabbed
simultaneously that doesn't sound great
I cannot push through a body no longer
functioning properly while this injury
being nerve related my body physically
will not keep going and it is absolutely
soul crushing so yeah I mean it's
already difficult enough to be an
athlete this level competing for what is
a much smaller athlete quota than we've
seen at previous Olympic Games before
and as you said already as an outside
shot because there are other athletes
that have put themselves higher in the
rankings so like everything seemed like
it was an uphill battle for her so I I
think it's also a nod to being a smart
athlete to like recognize that and be
able to stop yourself from trying to
push too hard on her own being able to
be like this sucks this is terrible but
it's the right thing to do my heart's
out to her as well but I think that this
is the right choice given how she
explained how her injury feels I do want
to be clear that she she did Express a
lot of positivity that you know a few
months of rest changing up what kind of
movement she's doing taking
weightlifting off the table right for a
little bit she thinks she can recover
fully which is great we want to hear
that we want healthy athletes so shout
out to Maddie for being public about it
being mature about it you know I will
say that I think this Olympic cycle has
been challenging for a lot of athletes
in the USA weightlifting system you have
a lot of young upand cominging I mean
the only we're likely to see only one
repeat Olympian on the women's side for
USA weing against Jordan D La Cruz right
wishing Maddie the best appreciate like
you said Phil the cander honesty
forthcoming this as she's shown here and
I like that how the cult I like how the
culture of strength Sports has evolved
from you know just push through it right
to like sometimes you can't right
sometimes the circumstances are a little
sacked against you and sometimes you get
unlucky hope to see her back not sure if
she's going to be going for the olymp
again in the next quad I kind of hope
she does personally moving on to another
injury related withdraw but but this
time on retirement Victoria long noted
strong woman who might have had the
hottest run in the history of the sport
of strong man on either men's or women's
sides former bodybuilder started
competing at the highest level in strong
women around like 2019 has basically
just had a five-year career maybe even a
Touch under fiveyear career at the
highest
ranks boy has it been a hot run she is
retiring yeah so you know this was also
news to everybody in the strength space
as well that's been covering Victoria La
through like her insane run that she's
had since 2019 so yes her first
competition was actually the world's
strongest woman in 2019 where she got
second place and then she didn't lose
again since that was it it was a silver
medal and then it was first places all
the way through until a retirement this
year after injuring herself at the
Arnold so it was during the max Elephant
bar deadlift that Victoria long suffered
a hamstring injury that pulled her out
of the compet I and then subsequently
afterward she announced that that would
then lead to her retiring from the sport
but she shared in her retirement in an
interview with Lauren shal that she had
a Five-Year Plan coming into the sport
and then after five years she was like
okay that that's that's it I was I was
gonna compete for five years she was a
bodybuilder as you mentioned beforehand
compete as a strong woman for five years
and then move on to other endeavors in
her life she spoke about how she's going
to get into law enforcement and such and
that's going to be her career going
forward but I mean a dominant career
that spanned let's just run do it real
quick if you'll if you'll allow me I'll
humor you Phil I'll humor you second
place world strongest women 2019 2021
America strongest woman first place
Arnold strongwoman Pro in 2022 first
place Shaw classic 2022 first place
America's strongest woman 2022 first
place Arnold strongwoman Classic 2023
first place and at that same event she
hit the Elephant bar deadlift record
that was only broken this year by Lucy
underdown Had Victoria long not gotten
injured she may have been able to take
the record back because nobody has ever
deadlifted like her before so just an
insane run it's also like an insane run
with covid right in the middle of it
right you notice there's no 2020 result
because there weren't competitions that
year we covered a lot of that a lot of
it like is the Arnold happening is it
not happening what are we doing like
there was a lot of coverage for that
yeah yeah a lot of circumstances I'm not
to say there weren't any competitions
that year because like things didn't
shut down till March but like you wonder
if she'd have another couple pieces of
Hardware there I don't know if it's
you'd wonder I think it's like obviously
expected she would have you know I I I
don't think there's I don't think that
one's like you know speculative for us
to be like yeah she would have won
everything that year you know her that
run is like the only thing I can compare
it to is Sandy kofax right Sandy kofax
had like an 11 year 10 or 11 year career
in Major League Baseball relatively
short for a picture but it's like one of
the greatest pictures of all time and
his stats are just like his hot streaks
were just the hottest streaks right I
think this is in the sport of strongman
on the women's side or the men's side
maybe the hottest
outside of like Marius panowski
outside of big Z at his
Peak you don't really get a lot of you
don't get like a run like this is a this
is a run right this was a run and to to
see Victoria long bow out now I mean I
get it you know she had a plan she
executed the plan and boy did she uh but
like it's it is a shame that we will not
be seeing her in major competitions
anymore because what a what a historic
run Victoria long
a fond farewell a career planned and
executed to Perfection kudos to you hope
you enjoy the next phase of your life
Thanks for the Memories they were
awesome they were a Thanks for the
Memories and the deadlifts they were
awesome all right speaking of Mitchell
Hooper Mitchell Hooper took to social
media recently he's coming off fresh off
an Arnold strongman classic win he's
prepping for world strongest man to
repeat his title Mitchell Hooper is
really interesting I've been fortunate
enough to spend some time in talking to
him on the barbend podcast Huber is a
clinical exercise physiologist right he
he's that first a strongman second by
his own admission this guy knows a lot
about the body he knows about training
he's competed in CrossFit he's run
marathons and now he's the World's
Strongest Man tipping the scales at over
350 pounds but he's also doing bar
muscleups at over 350 pounds this guy's
athletic as they
come had some really interesting things
to say about body fat because in the
sport of strong man we see a range of
body compositions right you have someone
like Evan singon who competes with
visible abs and then you have folks on
the other end of the spectrum who who
seem to have a higher body fat
percentage right now body fat percentage
is a little more than just what you can
kind of like visually look at and then
you have athletes who you know big Z
famously would lean out in the offseason
to carry less weight Hooper had some
really interesting things to say about
optimal body fat percentages for him the
fact that in strongman you probably want
some body fat and what this can mean for
getting strong man more popular in the
mainstream Phil can you give us a quick
rundown of what Hooper was talking about
here yeah so Hooper was uh talking about
how it's it is valuable to have a decent
amount of body fat on you as a strongman
athlete because you want to have that
body fat to protect your joints because
you're putting them under a lot of
stress when you're lifting heavy
implements we've seen all types of body
compositions across the Spectrum for
guys who have won the World's Strongest
Man multiple times over their careers
for Hooper he had hovered around 32%
body fat early on in his strongman
career and he sort of figured out that
the correct percentage for him is around
but under 30% you think that that's
really the the ceiling that anybody
should go for strongman competitively
which is around 30% you don't need to be
overly heavy you know even though Mass
moves Mass you don't need to be o overly
heavy in order to succeed H at the
highest level of competition so he's at
approximately 364 pounds that's where
he's currently doing those bar muscleups
but yeah he's he's capped himself at 30%
he thinks that that's also where
everybody else should be he says quote I
think I've started to find The Sweet
Spot I'm not sure I want to get much
leaner than I am right now because we do
need that cushion and protection for the
joints but also I don't want to be
unhealthy to an extent that it's going
to impact my long-term prognosis my
long-term risk of dying so he's keenly
aware of longevity in the sport and long
longevity after he retires from the
sport that also I we were talking about
athlete maturity that is something very
very important because we've seen guys
balloon up to weight that is not
sustainable only to win a title and then
back off I mean notoriously the most the
most famous one that comes to mind for
me is Eddie Hall when he was when he
deadlifted you know he was the first to
break 500 kilo kilos but he's ballooned
himself up to 400 over 400 pounds in
order to make that kind of lift win 2017
world strongest man then retired then
leaned out right we we we've seen that
strategy before and it's it's
interesting to see Hooper suggesting
that maybe we don't need to do that at
the highest level I do want to read one
more quote because Hooper is an exercise
physiologist and you know he has a
private practice I thought this was
pretty interesting and he said I love
strong man for people who might be
overweight to begin with if you know
someone or you have someone in your life
who is overweight naturally having
higher total mass even if they're not in
very good shape they will have a higher
muscle mass because they have to carry
around that body and Hooper generally
believes that strongman could be an
interesting method for folks who are
already overweight to start getting in
shape and start body recomposition right
they do have some that excess fat it
helps can help people get more mobile
help them get stronger and gradually
maybe change to a healthier body
composition while improving overall
health and wellness so interesting you
know strong man for Better Health
outcomes for people who are already a
bit overweight very interesting take and
something that you know if we get to
chat with Hooper again hopefully we will
I definitely want to ask him about and
also Mitchell Hooper is a guy who has a
lot going on I wouldn't be him surprised
to see him like release a training
program like how to get in strong man
and get healthier through strong man if
you're overweight or something like that
like I would not be surprised to see him
do that so M Hooper interesting take
something fun just to wrap up this
episode and hey sorry Mitchell but I'm
going to be I'm going to be asking we're
going to be asking about your body fat
percentage heading into competitions now
because we're just curious because
you're very smart you're very calculated
we want to know all the variables you're
crunching all the numbers you're
crunching that brings us to the end of
today's broadcast we covered a wide
range of things and most importantly I
want to say and and I don't think we
actually emphasize this enough on
strength weekly we talk about injuries
we talk about how injuries impact
careers we're wishing all the athletes
who have experienced injuries who we
cover we're wishing them speedy
recoveries it is news it changes the
competition landscape Victoria long
retiring changes the competition
landscape in strong women in the open
division for years to come Matti Rogers
pulling out of Paris contention changes
the landscape of competitive
weightlifting these are newsworthy but
at the same time we understand there are
real people and there are real bodies uh
that experience these injuries we don't
like seeing injuries we report on them
but I want to be very clear we are
wishing all these athletes speedy
recoveries and I personally I'm very
happy there is a trend toward long-term
Health outcomes when it comes to
strength Sports as Maddie Rogers has
kind of Illustrated and as Victoria long
has Illustrated with her retirement so
just something I wanted to say here
these are real people these are real
bodies they're experiencing real pain
and I I think it's easy to lose sight of
that and something that I really want to
hold myself accountable at in
Remembering so thanks for listening
folks appreciate it well that wraps up
strength weekly for this week I'm David
Thomas to joined by I'm Phil Blackman
thank you so much for watching all of
our Arnold coverage over the last three
over the past month uh if you want to
catch any more of it or recap on any it
head over to Barb ben.com but until then
we'll catch you next time cheers
[Music]
folks